Why is there — Okay. Okay. (Laughter)
لماذا يوجد — حسنًا حسنًا. (ضحك)
This is a cosmic mystery. Be solemn.
هذا لغز كوني. كونوا جادّين.
Why is there a world, why are we in it,
لماذا هناك عالم، ولماذا نحن فيه،
and why is there something rather than nothing at all?
ولماذا يوجد هنالك شيء بدلًا من لا شيء؟
I mean, this is the super ultimate "why" question?
أعني أن "لماذا" هو التساؤل الأزلي
So I'm going to talk about the mystery of existence,
لذلك سوف أتحدث عن سر الوجود،
the puzzle of existence,
لغز الوجود،
where we are now in addressing it,
أين نحن الآن من معالجته،
and why you should care,
ولماذا يجب عليكم الاهتمام،
and I hope you do care.
وأتمنى أن تهتموا.
The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer said that
قال الفيلسوف آرثر شوبنهاور ذلك
those who don't wonder about the contingency of their existence,
هؤلاء الذين لا يتسائلون عن صدفة وجودهم،
of the contingency of the world's existence,
عن صدفة وجود العالم،
are mentally deficient.
يعانون من نقص عقلي.
That's a little harsh, but still. (Laughter)
هذا قاس قليلًا، ولكن صحيح. (ضحك)
So this has been called the most sublime
لذلك قد عُرف هذا بأسمى تساؤل
and awesome mystery,
وأروع لغز،
the deepest and most far-reaching question
وأعمق وأصعب تساؤل
man can pose.
يمكن لإنسان تخيّله.
It's obsessed great thinkers.
لقد تسبب في هوس مفكرين عظماء.
Ludwig Wittgenstein, perhaps the greatest
ربما لودفيج وتجنشتاين هو أعظم
philosopher of the 20th century,
فيلسوف في القرن العشرين
was astonished that there should be a world at all.
كان مندهشًا لوجود العالم أصلًا.
He wrote in his "Tractatus," Proposition 4.66,
ذكر في كتابه " أطروحات" اقتراح ٤.٦٦،
"It is not how things are in the world
"ليس التساؤل حول كيفية وجود العالم
that is the mystical,
ذلك تصوف،
it's that the world exists."
لكن التساؤل هو في أصل الوجود."
And if you don't like taking your epigrams
وإذا كنت لا تحب أن تأخذ سخرياتك
from a philosopher, try a scientist.
من فيلسوف، جرب عالِم.
John Archibald Wheeler, one of the great physicists
جون أرتشيبالد ويلر، واحد من الفيزيائين العظماء
of the 20th century,
في القرن العشرين،
the teacher of Richard Feynman,
هو أستاذ ريتشارد فاينمان،
the coiner of the term "black hole,"
مخترع مصطلح "الثقب الأسود،"
he said, "I want to know
قال، "أريد أن أعرف
how come the quantum,
كيف وُجد الكم،
how come the universe, how come existence?"
وكيف وُجد الكون، وكيف وُجد الوجود؟"
And my friend Martin Amis —
وصديقي مارتن أميس —
sorry that I'll be doing a lot of name-dropping in this talk,
أعتذر، سأخبركم بأسماء كثيرة في هذا الحديث،
so get used to it —
لذا اعتادوا على الأمر —
my dear friend Martin Amis once said
قال صديقي العزيز مارتن أميس ذات مرة
that we're about five Einsteins away from answering
بأننا بحاجة إلى خمسة أشخاص مثل أينشتاين للإجابة
the mystery of where the universe came from.
على لغز من أين جاء الكون.
And I've no doubt there are five Einsteins
وأنا لا أشك بوجود خمسة أشخاص مثل أينشتاين
in the audience tonight.
في هذا الحضور الليلة.
Any Einsteins? Show of hands? No? No? No?
أيوجد أينشتاين؟ ارفع يدك؟ كلا؟
No Einsteins? Okay.
لا يوجد أينشتاين؟ حسنًا.
So this question, why is there something rather than nothing,
إذًا هذاالسؤال، لماذا هناك شيء بدل من لا شيء،
this sublime question, was posed rather late
طُرح هذا السؤال الجوهري في وقت متأخر
in intellectual history.
نواعًا ما من التاريخ الفكري.
It was towards the end of the 17th century,
كان قبالة نهاية القرن السابع عشر،
the philosopher Leibniz who asked it,
الفيلسوف لايبنتز الذي سأله،
a very smart guy, Leibniz,
شخص زكي جدًا، لايبنتز،
who invented the calculus
الذي اخترع حساب التفاضل والتكامل
independently of Isaac Newton, at about the same time,
بشكل مستقل عن إسحاق نيوتن في نفس الفترة،
but for Leibniz, who asked why is there something rather than nothing,
لكن بالنسبة للايبنتز، الذي سأل لماذا الوجود وليس العدم،
this was not a great mystery.
لم يكن هذا سر عظيم.
He either was or pretended to be
قد كان أو تظاهر بأنه
an Orthodox Christian in his metaphysical outlook,
مسيحي متدين بمظهره الميتافيزيقي الخارجي،
and he said it's obvious why the world exists:
حيث قال إنه واضح لماذا العالم موجود:
because God created it.
لأن الله خلقه.
And God created, indeed, out of nothing at all.
و خلق الله، في الواقع، من لا شيء على الإطلاق.
That's how powerful God is.
وهذا هو مدى قدرة الله.
He doesn't need any preexisting materials to fashion a world out of.
لا يحتاج إلى مواد أولية مسبقًا لخلق هذا العالم.
He can make it out of sheer nothingness,
يستطيع أن يخلق من العدم المطلق.
creation ex nihilo.
خلق من العدم.
And by the way, this is what
وبالمناسبة، هذا ما
most Americans today believe.
يؤمن به أكثر الأمريكان اليوم.
There is no mystery of existence for them.
لا يوجد أي غموض للوجود بالنسبة لهم.
God made it.
الله خلقه.
So let's put this in an equation.
إذًا دعونا نضع هذا في معادلة.
I don't have any slides so I'm going to mime my visuals,
ليس لدي أي شرائح لذلك أنا بصدد أن أقوم بتمثيل مرئياتي،
so use your imaginations.
لذا استخدموا مخيلتكم.
So it's God + nothing = the world.
إذًا الله + لا شيء = العالم.
Okay? Now that's the equation.
مضبوط؟ هذه هي المعادلة.
And so maybe you don't believe in God.
وهكذا قد لا تكون مؤمن بالله.
Maybe you're a scientific atheist
قد تكون عالم ملحد
or an unscientific atheist, and you don't believe in God,
أو ملحد غير علمي، و لا تؤمن بالله،
and you're not happy with it.
ولست سعيدًا بهذا الأمر.
By the way, even if we have this equation,
بالمناسبة، حتى لو لدينا هذه المعادلة،
God + nothing = the world,
الله + العدم = العالم،
there's already a problem:
هناك مشكلة بالفعل:
Why does God exist?
لماذا يوجد الله؟؟
God doesn't exist by logic alone
الله لا يوجد بالمنطق وحده
unless you believe the ontological argument,
إلا إن كنت تؤمن بالجدل الوجودي،
and I hope you don't, because it's not a good argument.
وآمل ألا تكونوا، لأنه جدل غير جيد.
So it's conceivable, if God were to exist,
إذًا من الممكن تخيله، لو كان الله في الوجود،
he might wonder, I'm eternal, I'm all-powerful,
قد يتساءل، أنا أبدي، وأنا قدير،
but where did I come from?
لكن من أين أتيت؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Whence then am I?
من أين إذًا أكون أنا؟
God speaks in a more formal English.
يتكلم الله بإنجليزية رسمية أكثر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so one theory is that God was so bored with
توجد نظرية مفادها أن الله كان ضجرًا
pondering the puzzle of His own existence
من التأمل في لغز وجوده
that He created the world just to distract himself.
لذلك خلق العالم فقط ليشغل نفسه.
But anyway, let's forget about God.
على كل حال، دعونا ننسى الله.
Take God out of the equation: We have
لنُخرج الله من المعادلة:
________ + nothing = the world.
لدينا ــــ + العدم = العالم.
Now, if you're a Buddhist,
الآن، لو كنت بوذيًا،
you might want to stop right there,
قد ترغب أن تتوقف هنا حقًا،
because essentially what you've got is
لأن في الأساس ما حصلت عليه هو
nothing = the world,
العدم = العالم،
and by symmetry of identity, that means
و في حال تطابق الهوية, ذلك يعني
the world = nothing. Okay?
العالم = العدم. مضبوط؟
And to a Buddhist, the world is just a whole lot of nothing.
وبالنسبة للبوذي، العالم هو مجرد الكثير من اللا شيء.
It's just a big cosmic vacuity.
إنه مجرد فراغ كوني كبير.
And we think there's a lot of something out there
و نحن نعتقد أن هناك الكثير من الشيء
but that's because we're enslaved by our desires.
لكن ذلك لأن رغباتنا تستعبدنا.
If we let our desires melt away,
لو تركنا رغباتنا تذوب بعيدًا،
we'll see the world for what it truly is,
سوف نرى العالم لما هو عليه حقًا،
a vacuity, nothingness,
الفراغ، والعدم،
and we'll slip into this happy state of nirvana
وسوف ننزلق في حالة سعادة قصوى
which has been defined as having
والتي تم تعريفها كامتلاكك فقط
just enough life to enjoy being dead. (Laughter)
حياة كافية لتستمتع بكونك ميت. (ضحك)
So that's the Buddhist thinking.
إذًا, هذا هو الفكر البوذي.
But I'm a Westerner, and I'm still concerned
لكني غربي، ولازلت مهتم
with the puzzle of existence, so I've got
بلغز الوجود, لذا لدي
________ + —
ـــ + ـــ
this is going to get serious in a minute, so —
سيصبح الأمر جادًا بعد قليل, إذًا ـــ
________ + nothing = the world.
ــــ + العدم = العالم.
What are we going to put in that blank?
ماذا سنضع في ذلك الفراغ؟
Well, how about science?
حسنًا، ماذا عن العلم؟
Science is our best guide to the nature of reality,
العلم هو مرشدنا الأفضل لطبيعة الواقع،
and the most fundamental science is physics.
والفيزياء هي أكثر علم أساسي.
That tells us what naked reality really is,
حيث تخبرنا ما هو الواقع المجرد فعلًا،
that reveals what I call TAUFOTU,
ذلك يكشف ما أطلق عليه (أ م ح ك)
the True And Ultimate Furniture Of The Universe.
الأداة المطلقة والحقيقية للكون.
So maybe physics can fill this blank,
إذًا قد تستطيع الفيزياء ملئ هذا الفراغ،
and indeed, since about the late 1960s or around 1970,
وفعلًا، منذ أواخر الستينيات أو حوالي السبعينيات،
physicists have purported to give
قد زعم علماء الفيزياء أن لديهم
a purely scientific explanation of how
شرح علمي بحت لكيف
a universe like ours could have popped into existence
أن كون مثل كوننا قد برز إلى الوجود
out of sheer nothingness,
من العدم المطلق،
a quantum fluctuation out of the void.
تقلب الكم من الفراغ.
Stephen Hawking is one of these physicists,
أحد هؤلاء العلماء هو ستيفن هوكينج،
more recently Alex Vilenkin,
ومؤخرًا ألكس فيلنكن،
and the whole thing has been popularized
وتم تعميم الأمر برمته
by another very fine physicist and friend of mine,
من قبل عالم الفيزياء والصديق الشخصي لي،
Lawrence Krauss, who wrote a book called
لورنس كراوس، الذي كتب كتاب يدعى
"A Universe from Nothing,"
"كون من عدم"
and Lawrence thinks that he's given —
يعتقد لورنس أن ـــ
he's a militant atheist, by the way,
هو ملحد متشدد، بالمناسبة،
so he's gotten God out of the picture.
لذلك أزال الله من الصورة ـــ
The laws of quantum field theory,
قوانين نظرية الحقل الكموَمي،
the state-of-the-art physics, can show how
أرقى نظريات الفيزياء، تستطيع أن تبين كيف
out of sheer nothingness,
للعدم المحض،
no space, no time, no matter, nothing,
حيث لا مساحة، ولا وقت، ولاشيء،
a little nugget of false vacuum
قليل من كتلة فراغ صلبة كاذبة
can fluctuate into existence,
يمكن أن ينقلب إلى كيان،
and then, by the miracle of inflation,
ثم، بواسطة معجزة التضخم،
blow up into this huge and variegated cosmos
ينفجر لينشئ هذا الكون الهائل المتنوع
we see around us.
الذي نراه من حولنا.
Okay, this is a really ingenious scenario.
حسنا, هذا حقًا سيناريو مبتكر.
It's very speculative. It's fascinating.
تأملي وجذاب جدًا.
But I've got a big problem with it,
لكنه أوجد لي مشكلة كبيرة،
and the problem is this:
تلك المشكلة هي:
It's a pseudo-religious point of view.
إنها وجهة شبه دينية.
Now, Lawrence thinks he's an atheist,
الآن، يظن لورنس نفسه ملحد،
but he's still in thrall to a religious worldview.
لكنه لا زال في عبودية النظرة الدينية.
He sees physical laws as being like divine commands.
يرى القوانين الفيزيائية كأوامر إلهية.
The laws of quantum field theory for him
قوانين نظرية الحقل الكموَمي بالنسبة له
are like fiat lux, "Let there be light."
أمر غير قابل للنقاش كآية في الإنجيل.
The laws have some sort of ontological power or clout
القوانين لها نوع من النفوذ والقوة الوجودية
that they can form the abyss,
والتي يمكنها تشكيل اللاتكون في ما قبل الخليقة،
that it's pregnant with being.
والتي هي حبلى بالوجود.
They can call a world into existence out of nothing.
تستطيع الخلق من العدم.
But that's a very primitive view of what
لكن هذه نظرة بدائية جدًا لتفسير
a physical law is, right?
قانون فيزيائي، صحيح؟
We know that physical laws are actually
نعلم أن القوانين الفيزيائية هي في الواقع
generalized descriptions of patterns and regularities
شروحات عامة لأنماط و أنظمة طبيعية
in the world.
في هذا العالم.
They don't exist outside the world.
لا وجود لها خارج هذا العالم.
They don't have any ontic cloud of their own.
ليس لها وجود قائم من تلقاء نفسه.
They can't call a world into existence
لا يمكن لهذه القوانين
out of nothingness.
أن تخلق الوجود من العدم.
That's a very primitive view
إنها نظرة بدائية جدًا
of what a scientific law is.
لتفسير قانون علمي.
And if you don't believe me on this,
وإن لم تصدقوني في هذا،
listen to Stephen Hawking,
استمعوا لـستيفن هوكينج،
who himself put forward a model of the cosmos
الذي وضع بنفسه نموذجًا لكون
that was self-contained,
مستقل بنفسه،
didn't require any outside cause, any creator,
ليس بحاجة لسبب خارجي، أو خالق،
and after proposing this,
وبعد افتراض ذلك،
Hawking admitted that he was still puzzled.
اعترف هوكينج أنه ما زال في حيرة.
He said, this model is just equations.
قال، هذا النموذج مجرد معادلات.
What breathes fire into the equations
ما الذي ينفخ الروح في هذه المعادلات
and creates a world for them to describe?
ويخلق عالم لهم ليوصف؟
He was puzzled by this,
أصابه هذا بالحيرة،
so equations themselves can't do the magic,
إذًا المعادلات نفسها لا تستطيع فعل السحر،
can't resolve the puzzle of existence.
لا تستطيع حل لغز الوجود.
And besides, even if the laws could do that,
وإلى جانب ذلك، حتى لو يمكن للقوانين فعل ذلك،
why this set of laws?
لماذا هذه المجموعة من القوانين؟
Why quantum field theory that describes
لماذا نظرية الحقل الكموَمي التي تصف
a universe with a certain number of forces
الكون بعدد محدد من القوى
and particles and so forth?
والجسيمات وما إلى ذلك؟
Why not a completely different set of laws?
لماذا لا يوجد مجموعة مختلفة تمامًا من القوانين؟
There are many, many mathematically consistent sets of laws.
يوجد العديد والعديد من مجموعات قوانين الرياضيات المترابطة.
Why not no laws at all? Why not sheer nothingness?
لماذا يوجد قوانين من الأساس؟ لماذا يوجد العدم المطلق؟
So this is a problem, believe it or not,
إذًا هذه مشكلة، صدق أو لا تصدق،
that reflective physicists really think a lot about,
تعكس أن الفيزيائيين يفكرون كثيرًا حقًا حولها،
and at this point they tend to go metaphysical,
وعند هذه النقطة يميلون للميتافيزيقيا،
say, well, maybe the set of laws
قائلون، حسنًا، ربما مجموعة القوانين
that describes our universe,
التي تصف كوننا،
it's just one set of laws
مجرد مجموعة واحدة من القوانين
and it describes one part of reality,
تشرح جانب واحد من الحقيقة،
but maybe every consistent set of laws
لكن ربما كل مجموعة قوانين مترابطة
describes another part of reality,
تصف جزءً آخر من الحقيقة،
and in fact all possible physical worlds
وفي الواقع كل العوالم المادية الممكنة
really exist, they're all out there.
الموجودة حقًا، جميعها من هناك.
We just see a little tiny part of reality
نحن نرى فقط جزءً صغيرًا من الواقع
that's described by the laws of quantum field theory,
الذي فسرته قوانين نظرية الحقل الكموَمي،
but there are many, many other worlds,
لكن هناك العديد من العوالم الأخرى،
parts of reality that are described
وأجزاء من الواقع وصفتها
by vastly different theories
نظريات مختلفة إلى حد كبير
that are different from ours in ways we can't imagine,
والتي هي مختلفة عن نظرياتنا بطريقة لا يمكننا تخيلها،
that are inconceivably exotic.
ذلك غريب لا يصدق.
Steven Weinberg, the father
ستيفن واينبرج، أبو
of the standard model of particle physics,
النموذج القياسي لفيزياء الجسيمات،
has actually flirted with this idea himself,
قد تعامل نفسه فعليًا مع هذه الفكرة،
that all possible realities actually exist.
أن كل الحقائق الممكنة موجودة فعليًا.
Also, a younger physicist, Max Tegmark,
أيضًا، ماكس تيجمارك، عالم الفيزياء الأصغر،
who believes that all mathematical structures exist,
الذي يعتقد أن جميع البنيات الرياضية موجودة،
and mathematical existence is the same thing
والوجود الرياضي هو نفس الشيء
as physical existence,
كالوجود الفيزيائي،
so we have this vastly rich multiverse
لذا لدينا هذا الكون المتعدد الغني إلى حد كبير
that encompasses every logical possibility.
الذي يشمل كل إمكانية منطقية.
Now, in taking this metaphysical way out,
الآن، باتخاذنا هذه الطريقة الميتافيزيقية،
these physicists and also philosophers are actually
هؤلاء الفيزيائيون والفلاسفة أيضًا يعودون
reaching back to a very old idea
للفكرة القديمة جدًا فعليًا
that goes back to Plato.
التي تنسب إلى أفلاطون.
It's the principle of plenitude or fecundity,
التي هي مبدأ الوفرة أو الخصوبة،
or the great chain of being,
أو سلسلة الوجود العظيمة،
that reality is actually as full as possible.
هذا الواقع فعليًا كامل قدر الإمكان.
It's as far removed from nothingness
منزوع بقدر من العدم
as it could possibly be.
قد يمكن أن يكون.
So we have these two extremes now.
إذًا لدينا الآن هذين النقيضين.
We have sheer nothingness on one side,
لدينا العدم المطلق على جهة،
and we have this vision of a reality
ولدينا هذه النظرة للوجود
that encompasses every conceivable world
التي تشمل كل العالم الممكن تصوره
at the other extreme: the fullest possible reality,
على الجهة المقابلة: أقصى واقع ممكن،
nothingness, the simplest possible reality.
العدم، أدنى واقع ممكن.
Now what's in between these two extremes?
الآن ماذا بين هذين النقيضين؟
There are all kinds of intermediate realities
هناك كل أنواع الحقائق الوسيطة
that include some things and leave out others.
التي تتضمن بعض الأشياء ويترك أخرى.
So one of these intermediate realities
إذًا واحدة من هذه الحقائق الوسطية
is, say, the most mathematically elegant reality,
هي، مثلا، الواقع الأكثر رقي رياضي،
that leaves out the inelegant bits,
ذلك يترك الجزئيات الأقل رقيًا،
the ugly asymmetries and so forth.
وعدم التناسق القبيح وما إلى ذلك.
Now, there are some physicists who will tell you
الآن، هناك بعض علماء الفيزياء سوف يخبرونكم
that we're actually living in the most elegant reality.
أننا في الحقيقة نعيش في أكثر واقع رقيًا.
I think that Brian Greene is in the audience,
أظن براين جرين حاضر بين الجمهور،
and he has written a book called "The Elegant Universe."
وقد ألّف كتابًا بعنوان "الكون الراقي."
He claims that the universe we live in mathematically
يدعي أن الكون الذي نعيش فيه
is very elegant.
راقي رياضيًا جدًا.
Don't believe him. (Laughter)
لا تصدقوه. (ضحك)
It's a pious hope, I wish it were true,
إنه أمل تقي، أتمنى لو كان حقيقة،
but I think the other day he admitted to me
لكني أعتقد اليوم التالي اعترف لي
it's really an ugly universe.
أن الكون حقًا قبيح.
It's stupidly constructed,
تم تشييده بغباء،
it's got way too many arbitrary coupling constants
حصلت على الكثير من ثوابت اقتران تعسفية
and mass ratios
ونسب جماعية
and superfluous families of elementary particles,
وأسر غير الضرورية لجسيمات أولية،
and what the hell is dark energy?
وما هي تلك الطاقة المظلمة؟
It's a stick and bubble gum contraption.
انه عصا وعلكة غريبة الشكل.
It's not an elegant universe. (Laughter)
انه ليس كون راقي. (ضحك)
And then there's the best of all possible worlds
ثم هناك أفضل من جميع العوالم الممكنة
in an ethical sense.
بالمعنى الأخلاقي.
You should get solemn now,
يجب أن تكونوا جادين الآن
because a world in which sentient beings
لأن عالم به الكائنات الحية
don't suffer needlessly,
لا تعاني بلا داعي،
in which there aren't things like
لا توجد به أشياء مثل
childhood cancer or the Holocaust.
سرطان الأطفال والإبادات الجماعية.
This is an ethical conception.
هذا هو المفهوم الأخلاقي.
Anyway, so between nothingness
على أي حال، بين العدم
and the fullest possible reality,
وأقصى واقع ممكن،
various special realities.
عوالم استثنائية متنوعة.
Nothingness is special. It's the simplest.
العدم استثنائي. إنه الأبسط.
Then there's the most elegant possible reality.
ثم هناك الواقع الممكن الأكثر رقيًا.
That's special.
ذلك استثنائي.
The fullest possible reality, that's special.
أقصى واقع ممكن، ذلك استثنائي.
But what are we leaving out here?
لكن ماذا نترك هنا؟
There's also just the crummy,
هناك أيضًا فقط الحقائق
generic realities
العامة التافهة.
that aren't special in any way,
تلك ليست استثنائية بأي حال،
that are sort of random.
تلك مجموعة عشوائية.
They're infinitely removed from nothingness,
إنها منزوعة بلا حدود من العدم،
but they fall infinitely short of complete fullness.
لكنها لا ترقى بلا حدود للكمال المكتمل.
They're a mixture of chaos and order,
إنها خليط من الفوضى والنظام،
of mathematical elegance and ugliness.
من الرقي الرياضي والقبح.
So I would describe these realities
إذًا أود أن أصف تلك الحقائق
as an infinite, mediocre, incomplete mess,
أنها لا حصر لها، ومتوسطة، وفوضى غير مكتملة،
a generic reality, a kind of cosmic junk shot.
وواقع عام، ونوع من اللقطات الكونية الغير مرغوب فيها.
And these realities,
وهذه الحقائق،
is there a deity in any of these realities?
هل هناك إله في أي من تلك الحقائق؟
Maybe, but the deity isn't perfect
ربما، ولكن هذا الإله ليس مثاليًا
like the Judeo-Christian deity.
مثل الإله اليهودي المسيحي.
The deity isn't all-good and all-powerful.
هذا الإله ليس القدير المحسن.
It might be instead 100 percent malevolent
بل قد يكون 100 بالمائة حاقد
but only 80 percent effective,
لكن مؤثر 80 بالمائة فقط،
which pretty much describes the world we see around us, I think. (Laughter)
الذي يصف إلى حد كبير العالم الذي نراه حولنا، أعتقد. (ضحك).
So I would like to propose that the resolution
إذًا أود أن اقترح أن الحل
to the mystery of existence
للغز الوجود
is that the reality we exist in
أن الواقع الذي نوجد به
is one of these generic realities.
واحد من تلك الحقائق العامة.
Reality has to turn out some way.
يجب على الواقع أن يتحول طريقة ما.
It can either turn out to be nothing
قد يتحول سواء ليكون لا شيء
or everything or something in between.
أو كل شيء أو شيئ ما بينهم.
So if it has some special feature,
إذًا لو لديه سمة استثنائية،
like being really elegant or really full
مثل كونه راقي حقًا أو كامل حقًا
or really simple, like nothingness,
أو بسيط حقًا، مثل العدم،
that would require an explanation.
قد يتطلب ذلك تفسير.
But if it's just one of these random, generic realities,
لكن لو كان مجرد واحد من تلك الحقائق العامة العشوائية،
there's no further explanation for it.
ليس هناك تفسير آخر له.
And indeed, I would say
وبالفعل، أود أن أقول
that's the reality we live in.
هذا هو الواقع الذي نعيش فيه.
That's what science is telling us.
هذا ما يخبرنا به العلم.
At the beginning of the week,
في بداية الأسبوع،
we got the exciting information that
حصلنا على معلومات مثيرة
the theory of inflation, which predicts a big,
أن نظرية التضخم، التي تتوقع
infinite, messy, arbitrary, pointless reality,
واقع كبير، لا حصر له وفوضوي، واعتباطي، وعبثي،
it's like a big frothing champagne
يشبه رغوة شامبانيا كبيرة
coming out of a bottle endlessly,
تخرج من زجاجة بشكل لا متناهي،
a vast universe, mostly a wasteland
كون شاسع، معظمه قفار
with little pockets of charm and order and peace,
مع جيوب صغيرة من السحر والنظام والسلام،
this has been confirmed,
وتم تأكيد هذا،
this inflationary scenario, by the observations
السيناريو التضخمي هذا، بواسطة الملاحظات
made by radio telescopes in Antarctica
تمت بواسطة تلسكوبات لاسلكية في القطب الجنوبي
that looked at the signature of the gravitational waves
التي كانت رصدت توقيع موجات الجاذبية
from just before the Big Bang.
من قبل الانفجار الكبير.
I'm sure you all know about this.
أنا متأكد أنكم جميعًا تعرفون هذا.
So anyway, I think there's some evidence
إذًا على أي حال، أعتقد هناك بعض الأدلة
that this really is the reality that we're stuck with.
أن هذا الوقع الذي نحن ملصقون به حقًا.
Now, why should you care?
الآن، لماذا علينا الاهتمام؟
Well — (Laughter) —
حسنا ـــ (ضحك) ـــ
the question, "Why does the world exist?"
السؤال، "لماذا الكون موجود؟"
that's the cosmic question, it sort of rhymes
ذلك سؤال كوني، وانه نوع من القوافي
with a more intimate question:
مع سؤال أكثر حميمية:
Why do I exist? Why do you exist?
لماذا أنا موجود؟ لماذا أنت موجود؟
you know, our existence would seem to be amazingly improbable,
تعرفون، وجودنا قد يبدو غير مُتوقع بصورة مذهلة
because there's an enormous number of genetically possible humans,
لأن هناك عدد كبير من البشر ممكن وراثيًا،
if you can compute it by looking at
إذا كان يمكنكم حسابه من النظر
the number of the genes and the number of alleles and so forth,
لعدد الجينات والبدائل وما إلى ذلك،
and a back-of-the-envelope calculation will tell you
وسوف يخبرنا الحساب سريع
there are about 10 to the 10,000th
أن هناك حوال 10 ل 10000
possible humans, genetically.
احتمالية بشر وراثية.
That's between a googol and a googolplex.
ذلك بين 10x100 و 10x10100.
And the number of the actual humans that have existed
والعدد الفعلي للبشر الذين وجدوا
is 100 billion, maybe 50 billion,
100 مليار، قد يكون 50 مليار،
an infinitesimal fraction, so all of us,
جزء متناهي الصغر، إذًا كلنا،
we've won this amazing cosmic lottery.
قد ربحنا هذا اليانصيب الكوني المذهل.
We're here. Okay.
نحن هنا. حسنًا.
So what kind of reality do we want to live in?
إذًا ما نوع الواقع الذي نود أن نعيش فيه؟
Do we want to live in a special reality?
هل نريد أن نحيا في واقع استثنائي؟
What if we were living in the most elegant possible reality?
ماذا لو كنا نعيش في الواقع الأكثر رقيًا؟
Imagine the existential pressure on us
تخيلوا الضغط الوجودي علينا
to live up to that, to be elegant,
لنرتقي إلى هذا، لنكون راقيين،
not to pull down the tone of it.
وليس لهدم تناغمة.
Or, what if we were living in the fullest possible reality?
أو، ماذا لو كنا نعيش في أقصى واقع ممكن؟
Well then our existence would be guaranteed,
إذًا كان وجودنا مضمون،
because every possible thing
لأن كل شيء ممكن
exists in that reality,
موجود في ذلك الواقع،
but our choices would be meaningless.
لكن خياراتنا لن يكون لها معنى.
If I really struggle morally and agonize
لو ناضلت أخلاقيًا حقًا وكافحت
and I decide to do the right thing,
و قررت فعل الأمر الصحيح،
what difference does it make,
ما الفارق الذي يصنعه،
because there are an infinite number
لأن هناك عدد لا حصر له
of versions of me
من النُسخ مني
also doing the right thing
وأيضًا يفعلون الصواب
and an infinite number doing the wrong thing.
وعدد لا حصر له يفعلون الخطأ.
So my choices are meaningless.
لذا أفعالي لا معنى لها.
So we don't want to live in that special reality.
اذًا لا نريد ان نعيش في ذلك العالم الاستثنائي.
And as for the special reality of nothingness,
وأما واقع استثنائي من العدم،
we wouldn't be having this conversation.
لم يكن علينا أن نقيم هذه المحاضرة.
So I think living in a generic reality that's mediocre,
إذًا أعتقد العيش في عالم عام هذا وسطي،
there are nasty bits and nice bits
هناك أمور جميلة وأخرى قبيحة
and we could make the nice bits bigger
وباستطاعتنا أن نضاعف الجميل
and the nasty bits smaller
ونقلل القبيح
and that gives us a kind of purpose in life.
وهذا يعطينا هدفًا للحياة.
The universe is absurd,
الكون سخيف،
but we can still construct a purpose,
لكنا لا زلنا نستطيع بناء هدف،
and that's a pretty good one,
وهذه فكرة جيدة جدًا
and the overall mediocrity of reality
والاعتدال الشامل في هذا الواقع
kind of resonates nicely with the mediocrity
نوع من الصدى الجميل للاعتدال
we all feel in the core of our being.
الذي نشعره في جوهر وجودنا.
And I know you feel it.
وأعلم أنكم تشعرون به.
I know you're all special,
أعلم أنكم كلكم متميزون،
but you're still kind of secretly mediocre,
لكن لا تزالون نوع من الوسطية سرًا،
don't you think?
ألا تعتقدون ذلك؟
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So anyway, you may say, this puzzle, the mystery of existence,
اذًا على أي حال، قد تقولون، هذا اللغز، سر الوجود،
it's just silly mystery-mongering.
مجرد لغز سخيف للترويج.
You're not astonished at the existence of the universe
أنتم لم تندهشوا بوجود الكون
and you're in good company.
وأنتم في مجموعة جيدة.
Bertrand Russell said,
قال بيرتراند راسل،
"I should say the universe is just there, and that's all."
"يجب أن أقول أن الكون موجود، وهذا كل شيء."
Just a brute fact.
مجرد حقيقة غاشمة.
And my professor at Columbia, Sidney Morgenbesser,
وأستاذي في كولومبيا، سيدني مورجينبسر،
a great philosophical wag,
مهرج فلسفي كبير،
when I said to him, "Professor Morgenbesser,
عندما قلت له، "أستاذ مورجينبسر،
why is there something rather than nothing?"
لماذا هناك شيء بدل من لا شيء؟"
And he said, "Oh, even if there was nothing,
قال، "حسنا، حتى لو كان هناك لا شيء،
you still wouldn't be satisfied."
لم تكن لترضى."
So — (Laughter) — okay.
إذًا ـــ (ضحك) ـــ حسنًا.
So you're not astonished. I don't care.
إذًا أنتم لم تندهشوا. لا أكترث.
But I will tell you something to conclude
لكني سأختم كلامي بقول
that I guarantee you will astonish you,
أضمن لكم أن تدهشكم،
because it's astonished all of the brilliant,
لأنها أدهشت كل الأشخاص الأذكياء
wonderful people I've met at this TED conference,
الرائعون الذين قد قابلتهم في مؤتمرات (تيد)،
when I've told them, and it's this:
حين قد أخبرتهم،
Never in my life have I had a cell phone.
أني لم أمتلك قط هاتفًا خلويًا في حياتي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)